玄黄端现 太极混沌如鸡蛋 随着
In the beginning there was darkness and then
轰的一声
BANG!
诞生了无尽膨胀的时间 空间和物质
giving birth to endless expanding  existence of time, space and matter.
现在所见超乎我们的想象
Now see futher that we ever imagined
超越了客观认知极限
beyond the limits of ours existence
那地方我们称之为"宇宙"
in the place that we called the Universe.
宇宙广阔无垠
The Universe is vast
神奇 电光交织
wonderous, electrified.
对那些寻找刺激的太空旅行者来说
But for space travellers that looking for thrill ride
去宇宙旅行是条不归路
it could be a one way ticket
去了则不再复返
It is a place from which you cannot return.
至少不是以你去时的形式回来
Or at least, not in the form that you went in.
没有人敢冒这个险
go and no one has dare to venture.
去环游银河这个致命的地方
take a virtual tour of the deadiest  placies of our galaxy
甚至银河以外
and beyond
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://www.hdcmct.com
历史频道·宇宙第一季第12集 最危险的地方
影片压制:暮云春树  字幕来源：射手网 调校：TIAN@CMCT 招募Q号: 76846146
这是终极的前沿探险--太空环游
It is the ultimate frontier adventure, Space Travel
但当你遨游在银河系的丛林中
But when trekking through the galactic jungles
你必须留意宇宙中的热区
One must steer clear of the cosmic, hot zones
那里充满了爆炸和陷阱
Places teeming with violence and intrigue.
那些危险的地方爆发力很强
There are dangerous places certainly  very energetic phenomena
爆发力比爆炸的原子弹还要强
That are a lot more powerful than  atomic bombs being detonated
能量无限
Infinitely more powerful.
宇宙似乎到处充满了爆炸
The universe does seem to be a very violent place.
似乎它的诞生就源于爆炸 熟知的"大爆炸理论"
It seems to have been born in a  violent explosion called "The Big Bang"
并且爆炸还在继续
And there is also violent processes going on.
2004年12月27日
On december 27, 2004
卫星录下了伟大的宇宙爆炸
Satellites picked up the greatest cosmic  explosion ever recorded
三万光年以外的一次爆炸
A blast 30,000 light-years away
爆炸威力可以轻易摧毁地球的外部大气层
Which had the power to briefly alter  our planet's upper atmosphere.
爆炸是由一颗磁星引起的
The blast was caused by a magnetar
磁星是太空中最稠密 最危险之一的星星
The densest and one of the most  dangerous stars in space.
一颗磁星的磁场力约是
The magnetic field strength of a magnetar is about
地球磁场力的千万亿倍
A thousand trillion times the magnetic field energy of the Earth.
拿刷卡做参照
And for reference
刷卡将清除信用卡上的信息
This would wipe the information off a credit card
这一动作在十万英里远的地方就能完成
At a distance of about 100,000 miles away.
十万英里差不多是距月球距离的一半
Now, this distance is sort of half  the distance of the moon
从天文学角度来说 十万英里是很短的
So it's very nearby by astronomical standards.
这些淘气的星球拥有宇宙中最强的磁场
These mischievous stars have the strongest magnetic field in the Universe.
在银河中被科学家们证实的磁星共12颗
Scientists have confirmed 12 of these  rare stars in our galaxy
可能会更多
And there may be more.
加州理工的布莱恩·卡梅伦
Caltech's Brian Cameron
在银河中寻找这些陌生的星球
Scans the milky way for these strange stars.
磁星是中子星的一个特殊类别
Magnetars are a special class of neutron stars
拥有极强的磁场
With ultra strong magnetic fields
宇宙中最稠密的物质形式
The densest form of matter in the Universe.
第一颗磁星被发现时 处于高能级状态
The first magnetar showed itself in  the form of a high-energy event
发现于70年代晚期
That was detected in the late'70s
虽然那时
Although at the time
我们并不知道那就是磁星
We didn't know that it was a magnetar.
直到90年代早期
It wasn't until the early'90s
研究人员指出
That researchers suggested that
这些物体被磁场控制着
these objects were dominated by magnetic fields
从而确立了磁星理论
And that the magnetar theory was actually confirmed.
磁星的形成基于超大行星的毁灭
Magnetars are born out of the  death throes of massive stars.
当一颗星灭亡时
When a star dies
它开始瓦解形成超新星
It begins to collapse and go supernova.
有时超新星的爆炸中心
Sometimes, a dense neutron star
会形成密集的中子星
Forms from the centers of that supernova explosion.
这一过程中
During the process
一些中子星变成了磁星
A few neutron stars become magnetars
拥有极强的磁场
Which possess a strong magnetic field.
这些行星放射出高能的X射线和伽马射线
These stars eject high-energy emissions  of x-rays and gamma rays.
我们认为一般的中子星诞生于
We think that normal neutron stars are born from regular stars
那种比太阳质量大10或20倍的正规星
That are something like 10 or 20 times the mass of the Sun.
但有证据显示
But there's evidence that
磁星更有可能诞生于甚至更大的行星
magnetars are born from possibly even more massive stars
那种比太阳质量大40倍的行星
Than this, something like 40 times the mass of the S un.
很明显
Typically
这么大质量的行星太重而不易形成中子星
A star of such mass would be  too heavy to form a neutron star.
相反它的质量将陷入黑洞中
Instead, its mass would collapse into a black hole.
黑洞的形成就是
Black holes are formed
把一定数目的质量填入一定的体积中
From cramming a certain amount  of mass in a certain volume.
无论如何
And for whatever reason
这些质量超大的行星 没有形成中子星的能力
These stars are unable to do that.
有个理论认为一些超大行星
One theory is that some massive stars
在爆炸为超新星前 经历失重过程
Undergo a weight loss program right  before exploding as a supernova
损失了90%的质量
Losing 90 percent of their mass.
就无法陷入黑洞
So instead of collapsing into a black hole
余下的部分变成了中子星
The emaciated star becomes a neutron star
拥有超强磁力的中子星
With extreme magnetic powers.
当磁力变得太强时
When the magnetic force gets incredibly strong
使磁星地面变形
It deforms the magnetar's crust
在它表面产生地震叫做"星震"
Creating seismic events called "starquakes" on its surface.
最终如果地表在压力下破裂
Eventually, if this crust breaks under the stress
磁场使它进入低能状态
And the magnetic field reconfigures  itself into a lower energy state
当这些发生时
And when this happens
爆发出了火球 飞离星球边缘
A fireball is launched off the side of the star.
所以 我们认为中子星表面的星震
So starquakes on neutron stars' surfaces are thought to
产生了我们看见这些巨大的火焰
give rise to these giant flares that we see.
磁星出现这些火焰后
After a magnetar undergoes one of these flares
比银河里所有星星都要亮
It outshines all the stars in the galaxy
火焰将持续仅十分之一秒
For a few--For the few tenths of  a second that it's taking place.
巨大的火焰里是
Within these giant flares
以光速传播的伽马射线的短暂爆炸
Are short bursts of gamma rays,  which move at the speed of light.
来自磁星的巨大火焰就是伽马射线爆炸
The giant flares from magnetars are gamma ray bursts.
它们持续不久 不到一秒钟
They're very short in duration, Less than a second
比起其他伽马射线爆炸来说
And have very hard x-ray spectra
它们的X射线光谱很固定
Compared to another class of gamma ray bursts.
如果太空漫游者偏离了航线
If a deep space traveler veered off course
不幸遇到超大行星
And was unlucky enough
绕过它则需要700英里路程
To pass within 700 miles of one of these massive objects
结果是很恐怖的
The consequences would be horrific.
磁星的磁场
The magnetic field of the magnetar
能毫不夸张地扭曲人体内的原子
Can literally warp the atoms in human flesh
它的引力能将一个人撕碎
And its gravitational forces would tear a person apart.
那么太阳系中一颗磁星将何时
So then, how close would a magnetar have to be
引发大灾难呢？
To wreak havoc in our solar system?
有人认为
Some suggest
就算19光年远的一颗磁星爆炸
That a blast from a magnetar even 10 light-years away
也将引起宇宙混乱
Could produce cosmic chaos
将会破坏我们的臭氧层
That would destroy our ozone layer
导致大量生物灭绝
And cause mass extinctions.
但你知道那样发生的几率很小
The chances of that happening are so low that, you know
几乎是不可能的
They're completely implausible.
这种几率与
It would be no different than
正规星穿过太阳系一样不太可能
a regular star passing through the solar system.
我们知道正规星
And we know that a regular star
自太阳系形成以来
Has not passed through the solar system
就从没进入过太阳系
Since this solar system was formed.
科学家认为
Scientists think
磁星寿命只有几千年
That magnetars are only a few thousand years old
一万年后它们会变暗淡
And will become dim after 10,000 years.
我们现在才刚开始了解
We're just now starting to understand
磁星的生命周期
The life cycle of magnetars.
我们认为它们还很年轻
We think that they're very young
但具体有多年轻还不知道
But how young is still uncertain.
除磁星之外
In addition to magnetars
通过卫星和地面观察站
Satellites and ground-based observatories
人们还发现了 在太空中还有其它火爆的星球
Have been picking up other violent things in space.
科学家们现已确定
Scientists have now confirmed
一种幻影般的力量存在
The existence of a phantom-like force
而且很强大
That's so strong
这有可能是宇宙中最邪恶的现象
That it might very well be the most vicious phenomenon in the Universe.
鬼祟的这种力量萦绕于每个星系
Stealthy villains haunt each and every galaxy.
它就像野兽般把途经的星球撕碎
One particular beast tears up anything in its path
并把星球吞并 就像吃开胃小菜
And gobbles it down like a cocktail hors d'oeuvre.
它是宇宙中最怪异 最具破坏性的
It's one of the most bizarre and destructive phenomenon
现象之一
In the Universe
黑洞
A black hole.
我认为黑洞
I think a black hole
是宇宙中力量最强大的地方
Is the place which is more violent than anywhere else in our Universe.
就像走到了世界尽头
It's like going over the edge
无回头之路
And you can't get back.
我觉得是种致命的吸引
It's fatal attraction, I suppose.
宇宙中的黑洞处
A black hole is a region of space
地心引力非常大
Where the pull of gravity is so immense
什么的逃不掉 就连光也逃不掉
That nothing can escape it not even light.
天体 物理 运动三项全能的
Astrophysicist and triathlete
费约·奥济尔
Feryal Ozel
尝试去解决
Is attempting to unlock
黑洞引力周围的谜团
The mysteries surrounding this elusive cosmic force.
黑洞里
In a black hole
引力太强大
The gravity is so strong
没有其他力能竞争得过它
That no other force can compete with it
任何物质都缩解为单个点
So everything collapses to a single point.
奥济尔说
Ozel says
只要靠近黑洞 无论什么东西
Whatever has a close encounter with a black hole
都会成为潮汐般引力的牺牲品
Will fall victim to its relentless tidal force of gravity.
想象一下你在游泳池里游泳
Imagine you're swimming in a pool
没有水流
And there is no current
你可以随意向哪个方向游
You can go whichever direction you want.
现在假设你不在游泳池里游泳
Now, imagine, you're taken out of this pool
而是在河里游泳
And you're in a river.
想象一下河中水流非常强
Imagine a current that is much, much, much stronger
你只能朝一个方向运动
That the only direction that you could go
那就是水流方向
Would be with this current.
太空中黑洞附近地方 就类似于这条奔流的河
The space around a black hole acts like this wild river.
你摆脱不了这股强大的拖力
You could never fight this enormous drag that you feel.
当一个物体接近黑洞边缘时
As an object approaches the edge of a black hole
黑洞边缘叫做"视界"
Called the "event horizon,"
这是不归路的临界点
It reaches the point of no return.
随你离"视界"越来越近
As you come closer and closer to this event horizon
你就越靠近
You would already be approaching
太空这种极快的运动
This extremely fast motion of space under you
接下来你唯一的移动方向就是进入黑洞
And your only future direction is now into the black hole.
对于黑洞本身
The idea of the black hole
作为一个洞有时令人有点费解
As a hole sometimes can be a little bit confusing.
它究竟是什么
What it really is
某种意义上说
In some sense
它是一个你永远也回不来的地方
It's a place from which you can't return
至少不是以你进入的方式回来
Or at least, not in the form in which you went in.
黑洞难以发现
Black holes are difficult to detect
因为就像这名字暗示的一样
Because as the name suggests
你看不见它 因为它是黑暗的
You cannot see one by itself because it's black.
但科学家们
But scientists
已发现一个黑洞
Have spotted a black hole
就在它侵蚀太空中其它物质的时候
When its gravity affects something else in space
如侵吞一颗路过的行星
Such as a passing star.
一个完全隔绝的黑洞是无法看见的
A completely isolated black hole would not be visible.
从黑洞那我们真正看到的
What we really see from a black hole
实际是黑洞周围盘旋的强放射性物质
Is actually the hot material that's swirling around it
正被吸入其中
And that's being sucked into it.
所以这些强力的黑洞附近
So, in the neighborhood of these powerful black holes
你会发现许多辐射
You'll get a lot of radiation
辐射的产生由于黑洞
Resulting from the black hole
吸入物质 拉伸它 绞曲它
Pulling in material - And stretching it - And twisting it
辐射就发生在物质坠入黑洞过程中
As it's falling in black holes
黑洞侵食着近距离的所有物质
Black holes consuming anything in close range
并且有几十亿以上的黑洞潜伏于宇宙中
And there are billions upon billions of them prowling the Universe.
天体物理学家安德里亚·盖兹
Astrophysicist Andrea Ghez
是世界主要黑洞猎手之一
Is one of the world's leading black hole hunters.
黑洞并不挑食
Black holes are not picky eaters.
见一个吃一个
They'll dine on whatever get nearby
它们很乐意吞气体
So they will happily eat gas
它们也很乐意吞并一颗恒星或行星
They will happily consume a star or a planet.
当它吸食一个行星时
When a black hole dines on a star
它不会先把它撕碎
It does so first by tearing it apart.
你可以想象成软软的油灰被拉伸
And you might think of silly putty being stretched out
然后流动在水似的物体上
And then it just streams on in sort of like water
接着被慢慢卷入
Going down a drain.
完全就像磨面粉
It's completely pulverized.
我们认为黑洞的产生
Black holes are produced, we believe
是由于超大恒星的瓦解
By the collapse of the core of a massive star
那种比太阳质量大25~30倍的恒星
Something like 25 or 30 times the mass of the Sun or more.
当恒星的生命快结束时
When it comes to the end of its lifetime
超大恒星的地心开始燃烧
A massive star burns its core
一直烧掉氦 碳 氮 氧
All the way past helium, carbon, nitrogen, oxygen
烧到最后只剩没有核能的铁
All the way to iron which has no more nuclear fuel.
当铁心重建出一块物质时
And when that iron core builds up to a certain mass
会出现它自身无法再支撑的一点
There comes a point where it can no longer support itself
这时铁心崩溃
And the core will collapse
直到形成黑洞
All the way to a black hole
同时形成一颗超新星
Producing at the same time a supernova.
超新星传送出超大能量的爆炸
The supernova sends out explosive amounts of energy
所以超新星附近的物质将成灰烬
So anything in its vicinity will get obliterated.
然后爆炸后的残迹
Then, the remnants of the explosion
坠入新形成的黑洞
fall into a newly formed black hole.
似乎
And it seems
黑洞吸引的关键在于向心引力
The key to the black holes' allure is gravity.
向心引力把物质拉聚在一起
Gravity will pull things around
就像太阳把各大行星拉聚在一起一样
Just like the Sun's gravity pulls the planets around.
实际上
In fact
行星的大部分时光都是绕黑洞轨道和陆地飞行
Stars will happily orbit the black hole for most of its life
而不会被吸入其中
And won't actually be sucked in.
这些行星实际很安全
These stars are actually safe
不会被黑洞吸引而脱离轨道
From the fatal attraction of the black hole
但如果你要大胆靠近的话
But if you do venture too close
非常接近黑洞边缘
Like extremely close to the edge
你就会被吸入其中
Then you do get sucked in.
科学家认为
Scientists believe there are
我们银河系中 存在难捉摸的黑洞
Millions of wayward black holes throughout our galaxy, the milky way.
因为我们不能够看见它们
And because we can't readily see them
可能附近就有一个
One could be right next door.
那么到底离黑洞多近
So how close does something have to be
我们就会被吸入其中呢？
To get sucked into a black hole?
离黑洞约地球到太阳间距离这么远
Too close to a black hole is about the distance
就算很近了
Between the sun and the earth
但那确实太近了
But that is certainly too close.
对未来太空旅行者死于黑洞
For future space travelers, death by a black hole
会是种壮烈的死法
Would be a violent way to go.
黑洞杀死你的方法
The method by which a black hole could kill you
取决于黑洞有多大
Depends on how big the black hole is.
黑洞分两类
They come in two categories.
它们大部分是呈星状的黑洞
Most of them are the stellar-mass black holes
质量是太阳的5~30倍
Which are five to 30 times the mass of our sun.
如果是星状的黑洞
If the black hole is stellar-sized
黑洞周围潮汐般的力量大得足以
Then the tidal forces near the black hole is strong enough
把你整齐地撕裂
That it will tear you apart tidily
甚至在视界以外
Even well outside the event horizon.
就算你想坠入黑洞
If you wanted to fall into a black hole
你一定不会想坠入这一种黑洞
You certainly wouldn't want to fall into one of those.
它将把你撕成面条
It will spaghettify you.
但除了星状黑洞
But in addition to the stellar-sized black holes
还有一种庞大黑洞
There are others that are mammoth
是太阳质量的百万至十亿倍
Millions to a billion times the mass of the sun.
现在科学家们相信
And now, scientists believe
这种庞然大物占据着每个星系的中央位置 银河系也是
That these monsters hold center court in every galaxy including our own.
黑洞
Black holes
它们是
They're one
太空中最神秘 最具潜在危险的奇物之一
Of the most mysterious and potentially dangerous oddities in space.
一个黑洞胃口非常大
A black hole has a ravenous appetite.
吞食途经的任何物质
It sucks in everything in its path
吐出残渣
And spits out what it doesn't devour.
现在科学家们发现
And now, scientists have discovered
存在超大质量黑洞
There are supermassive black holes
比它同族的星状黑洞要大百万倍
Which are millions of times bigger than their stellar mass cousins.
证据显示
And evidence suggests
超大质量黑洞诞生于宇宙大爆炸之后
That supermassive black holes were born after the big bang
产生于宇宙之初
When the Universe was first created.
它们的形成
The leading idea is that they would have formed
就像超大行星瓦解形成的
Just like the stellar black holes from the collapse
星状黑洞的形成一样
Of the core of a massive star.
但它们会长大 依靠吸食
But then they grew by feeding grossly
与它们相撞的其他星系的气体
From the gas from other galaxies which collided with them.
科学家们发现
Scientists have discovered
这些黑色怪物
That these black ogres
在星系的中心施展它们的力量
Wield their power in the center of galaxies.
超大质量黑洞就处于星系的中心
The supermassive black holes are at the center of the galaxy
很可能是因为
Most likely because
它们是星系中最庞大的物体
They are the most massive object within the galaxy.
庞大物体都趋于向心靠拢
Massive objects tend to sink to the middle
所以你总是发现它们处于星系的中心
So you'll always find them at the center of a galaxy.
有很长一段时间 科学家们不知道
For a long time, scientists didn't think
超大质量黑洞存在于我们的星系
A supermassive black hole existed in our neck of the Universe
银河系
The milky way.
但在1995年
But in 1995
天体物理学家安德里亚·盖兹
Astrophysicist Andrea Ghez
开始证明超大质量黑洞的存在
Set out to prove one exists.
我们用了十年多时间完成一个实验
We've done an experiment over the last 10 years
去索求这个问题:
To ask the question
我们星系中央会有超大质量黑洞吗？
is there a supermassive black hole at the center of our galaxy
我们的试验方法
And the way we did this experiment
是用我们星系中央行星的移动
Is to use the motions of stars at the center of our galaxy
来测试是否有大量的物质
To test whether or not there's a large amount of mass
存在于一个很小的空间
Inside a very small volume.
这就是黑洞存在的证据
And that's the proof of a black hole.
在夏威夷的凯克天文台
At the Keck Observatory in Hawaii
配备有全球最大的望远镜之一
Which houses one of the largest telescopes in the world
盖兹开始用
Ghez began using
一种先锋科技 叫做"适应性光学仪器"
A groundbreaking technology called "adaptive optics"
能聚焦看到很远的物体
Which brings into focus far away objects.
这是不用"适应性光学仪器"的结果
So this is without adaptive optics.
如你所见
This is what you would see.
在这个大正方形里什么也没有
In this big square, there's nothing.
开启适应性光学仪器
We turn adaptive optics on
你就可以看见星星了
And you see the stars.
这块区域里的行星
This region contains the stars
是我们实验的关键
That provide the keys to our experiment.
我们要看看它们如何运动
So we wanna watch how these stars move.
盖兹注意到有一大群行星
Ghez noticed that there was a large cluster of stars
绕着我们星系中心的不明物体旋转
Orbiting around an invisible object at the center of our galaxy
而且它们的移动速率异常的快
And they were moving at an unusually rapid rate.
我们实际上看到的这些行星
So we can actually see these stars
非常靠近我们星系的中心
That are really close to the center
我们可以看到它们在中心处绕动
And we can watch them go around.
这些行星在黑洞周围转动
Those stars go around the black hole
就像行星绕着太阳转动一样
Just the way the planets orbit the Sun.
绕行轨道告诉我们
The orbits tell us
黑洞所在的地方
Where the black hole is
它就位于图中的星形处
So it's located right where the star is.
那是我们星系的中心
That's the center of our galaxy.
一些细节如:
And the details
这些行星绕行得有多快
Of exactly how fast these stars are going around
轨道有多紧密
And how tight the orbits are
向我们透露了黑洞的质量
Tells us the mass of the black hole
我们现今认为
Which we think today
它的质量是太阳质量的四百万倍
Is four million times the mass of our Sun.
对盖兹来说
For Ghez
证明一个超大质量黑洞确实存在于
Confirming that a supermassive black hole indeed exists
我们星系的中央
At the heart of our galaxy
意义好比登上珠峰
Was like summiting Mount Everest.
在我们星系的中央发现超大质量黑洞
It was incredibly exciting to discover
令我无比兴奋
The supermassive black hole at the center of our galaxy
因为我们解决了曾经写下的问题
Simply because it was a question we had set out to address.
问题是"存在超大质量黑洞吗"？
The question, "is there a supermassive black hole?"
我们能够设计实验来认识它
And we could design an experiment that actually got at it.
天体物理学家安德鲁·汉密尔顿说
Astrophysicist Andrew Hamilton says
死于超大质量黑洞
death by a supermassive black hole
与死于另一种较小的星形黑洞会有很大不同
would be much different than by a smaller stellar mass relative.
如果你想去旅行
If you wanna go and be a tourist
想要跌入黑洞的终极经历
And have the ultimate experience of falling inside a black hole
发现那里有些什么
And finding out what's really there
那么去超大质量黑洞旅行吧
Go visit a supermassive black hole
更痛快
Much better idea ,
不同于星形黑洞
Unlike a stellar black hole
因为在你进入星形黑洞涡流前 它已把你撕成碎屑
Which would rip you to shreds, before entering its deadly vortex
太空探险者可以体验
A space explorer could actually experience
自由坠入超大质量黑洞的感觉
Free falling inside a supermassive black hole.
坠入超大质量黑洞里面
Inside of a supermassive black hole
结果是尽管黑洞质量很大
it turns out that even though the black hole is more massive
它的体积也很大
It's also much larger in size.
这意味着
And that means
这种向心引力很弱
That the type of forces are weak enough
以至于你可以穿过"视界"
That you could pass through the event horizon
深深跌入黑洞里面
And fall deep inside the black hole
而不被整齐地撕裂
Without being tidily torn apart.
但是 深入黑洞里面后
But, deep down inside the black hole
黑洞自转的离心力
The centrifugal force of the rotation of the black hole
驱使你向外移
Provides effectively a repulsion.
如果黑洞中有一点物质的话
If there's any matter at all inside it
向内跌的物质
Then stuff that's falling in
将会撞上向外飞溅的物质
Will tend to collide with stuff that's trying to get out.
这种高能量碰撞的结果
And the result of that collision of energies
将导致难以想象的 高热稠密等离子体混乱大漩涡
Is an unimaginably chaotic maelstrom of super hot dense plasma.
那样的话
And in that case
你将面临被烘烤的命运
Your fate is that it can roast you.
那么到底要多近太空旅行者才会被吸入
So how close would space travelers have to be to get sucked
星系中央的超大质量黑洞中呢？
Into a supermassive black hole in the center of a galaxy?
对超大质量黑洞来说
For a supermassive black hole
从黑洞中心到你感到它的作用的距离
You would have to be about a million to a billion miles
约百万到十亿英里远
From the black hole to feel its influence.
若干年后
Over the years
钱德拉射线天文台
The Chandra x-ray Observatory
捕捉到银河中
Has caught our galaxy's
超大质量黑洞吞噬宇宙物质的画面
Supermassive black hole nibbling on cosmic matter
并不是像其它超大质量黑洞那样活跃
Not bingeing like other supermassive black holes.
我们银河系的黑洞比起其它黑洞来说并不活跃
Our black hole is, today, inactive, compared to other black holes.
我们的星系中央的气体含量很少
Our galaxy has very little gas at the center
所以实际上我们星系的黑洞能吃到的物质很少
And so, there's nothing really for the black hole to feed on.
它吃得不多
It's not eating very much.
它正处于挨饿节食期
It's going on a bit of starvation diet.
我们星系的超大质量黑洞似乎在斋戒
Our galaxy's supermassive black hole appears to be fasting.
这部分是因为
This is partly due to the fact
随着银河年龄增大
That as a galaxy ages
能吞食得到的物质越来越少
Less and less matter is present for it to gorge on.
但在将来
But, in the future
如果在银河中心
It might be quite a bit more active
它能得到充足的新鲜气体供应的话 它可能会变得更活跃些
If it ever gets a fresh supply of gas at its center to feed off of
恢复我们的超大质量黑洞食欲的一个办法
One way to rejuvenate our supermassive black hole's appetite
就是与另一个星系相撞
Is to collide with another galaxy.
听着难以置信？
Sound implausible?
两百万光年远处
Two million light-years away
我们系最近的邻居仙女星系
Our closest neighbor, the Andromeda galaxy
正以75英里每秒的速度冲向我们
Is charging toward us at almost 75 miles per second
或是说270 000英里每小时
Or 270,000 miles per hour.
在未来
In the future
科学家们预言这两个星系会相撞
Scientists predict the two galaxies will collide
由于冲撞
And upon impact
较大的星系将会产生
The larger galaxy may engage in
宇宙中最原始的运动之一
one of the most primitive acts known in the Universe.
最野蛮的仪式之一
It's one of the most barbaric rituals in space
较大星系吞并较小的星系
A larger galaxy eats a smaller one.
这幅场景不是科幻小说作家的幻想
The scenario isn't a science fiction writer's fantasy
它是宇宙真实的写照
It's a cosmic reality.
叫做"星系吞食"
It's called "galactic cannibalism."
当两星系迎头相撞时
The ghastly event can occur on the celestial highway
这惊人的一幕就发生了
When two galaxies have a head-on collision
两星系最终融合在一起 但不是和睦的合并
Both eventually melt together in a less than harmonious merger.
星系非常暴力
If you're a galaxy, it's very violent.
会把你撕成碎片
You're torn to shreds.
约书亚·巴尼斯研习星系融合
Joshua Barnes studies galaxy mergers.
表现得像犯罪现场调查者
Acting like a crime scene investigator
他也承认他的研究有点类似观察车祸
He admits his research is a bit like inspecting a car crash.
想象你遇到一个车祸现场
Imagine that you come across the scene of a car crash
只有遇难的车辆没有目击者
Two wrecked vehicles but no witnesses
没人告诉你发生过什么
Nobody to tell you what happened
能调查的只有现场的证据
All you have is the physical evidence.
当我们研究星系碰撞时
That's basically what we have to do
基本上就是这样研究的
When we study colliding galaxies.
没有星系碰撞的目击者
So there are no witnesses to a galactic collision.
能调查的只有目前星系撞后的状态
All that you have is the present state of the wreckage.
所以你得开展一系列调查
So you have to conduct a sort of forensic investigation
来弄清楚
To try and figure out
以前发生过些什么
what happened on the basis of what you have today.
如果他们迎头相撞 你可以知道
If they collided head on , You would know
因为可以找到压碎的前端
Because the fronts were squashed up.
如果它们侧边相撞
And if they, say, side-swiped each other
其实在星系相撞中 这种侧边相撞更有可能
Which is actually more likely in galactic collisions
侧边撞留下的破坏痕迹又是完全不同的
That would leave you a completely different pattern of wreckage
你可以区别出来
And you could interpret that.
是什么引起星系融合的呢？
So what causes galaxy mergers?
万有引力
It's gravity.
宇宙中的任何物质都是在太空中自由穿梭
Everything in the universe is falling freely through space
对两个像星系这样大的两物体
And when you've got two large objects like galaxies
它们相互的万有引力把它们拉近
Their mutual gravity pulls them together
导致相互靠近
So they fall into each other.
确实就是万有引力把物体拉聚在一起
So it's really just the force of gravity pulling things around.
我们今天看到的星系碰撞
The galaxies that we're seeing colliding today
它们大多都是100到150亿年前
Most of them have been bound and destined to collide
就注定要撞在一起的
For upwards of 10--15 billion years
现在只是在完成它们的第一次碰撞而已
And they're only now just making it to that first collision.
我们银河系
Our own galaxy, the Milky Way
正在移向毗邻的仙女星系
Is moving toward our neighbor, Andromeda.
两个星系都呈螺线形
Both galaxies are spiral in shape
但是仙女星系约是超大质量黑洞质量两倍
But andromeda is about twice as massive with a supermassive black hole
是太阳质量3千万倍
The mass of 30 million suns.
当两星系相互靠拢时
It'll look a lot like a dance.
看起来就像在舞蹈
When you see the two galaxies come close together
它们如舞蹈般绕着对方
So they kind of dance around each other
越靠越近 越移越快
Getting closer and closer, moving faster and faster
在它们最终聚在一起前
Before they finally come together.
在碰撞那一点
But at the point of impact,
星系的舞蹈比人类的脚尖旋转复杂得多
These galactic dancers will do more than pirouette.
每个星系都有行星构成的螺线圆盘
Each one has a spiral disc of stars
螺线圆盘外围
And then surrounding that,
有一层暗物质光圈 人眼是不可见的
A halo of dark matter, invisible material
但我们能够探测到它的引力场
That we can detect by its gravitational field.
这两层暗光圈空间范围更大
These two dark halos, which are much larger
两星系经过时 暗光圈会叠在一起
Will overlap as the galaxies pass by.
随着两星系螺线式环绕对方 最后越来越近
Eventually, as the two galaxies spiral around each other closer and closer
你就再也区分不开它们了
You can no longer distinguish them as separate systems
最终 核聚在一起
And finally, the nuclei merge.
仙女星系与银河系冲撞时
When Andromeda and the Milky Way collide
银河系将会
That's going
遭到最大的冲撞
To be the biggest collision that the Milky Way has seen
50亿年来一遇
Something like five billion years time.
好消息是我们太阳系
The good news is that we, the solar system
能够正面观看到
Will have a grandstand view.
两星系冲撞的经过
What will happen is the two galaxies
它们的螺线圆盘
Their spiral discs
将被整齐地撕裂
Are gonna get tidily torn apart into fantastical shapes.
当圆盘靠近对方时
When the discs start to get close to each other
它们将扔掉长长的行星彩带
They'll throw off long streamers of stars
所谓的"潮汐尾翼"
So-called "tidal tails."
对于太阳和太阳系来说
And what happens to the Sun and the solar system
我们是否会被扔出去呢？
Should we still be around
实际情形很难预测
It really is hard to predict.
我们可能有幸成为其中的一条"潮汐尾翼"
We could get lucky and be on one of those tidal tails
飞出圆盘时可以鸟瞰到冲撞的整个过程
And get a sort of bird's eye view of the whole process as we fly out
或者我们有可能被吸住
Or we could get thrown into an orbit
卷入正在合并的星系的中央
Plunging towards the center of the merging galaxies.
基本上是难以预测的
There's basically no way to say.
星系合并过程中
During the merger
如果我们太阳系穿过仙女系外圈或边缘
If our solar system moves through the suburbs or the edges of Andromeda
那可能就什么也看不到
We might not notice anything.
另一方面
On the other hand
无数的行星和太空物质
Countless stars and space material
可能会飞向我们太阳系
Could be propelled towards the planets
可能会扰乱太阳系行星的运行轨道
Potentially disrupting their orbits around the sun.
而且整个银河系可能面临大变动
Moreover, the entire galaxy could face cosmic upheaval.
我们可以推论出
We could have consequences
结果是很危险的
Which would nonetheless be dangerous.
首先 我们星系可能
First of all, we could have
在星系合并后形成许多行星
A lot of star formations as a consequence of the merger.
目前银河系和仙女系都有
Currently, both the Milky Way and Andromeda galaxy
很多星际气体
Have plenty of interstellar gas
这是行星形成的原材料
The raw material from which stars are born.
那意味着
Now, that would mean
许多"零龄主序后星"  "超新星"会远离我们而去
A lot more evolved stars, supernova going off in our vicinity
这一离去将导致震波 冲击波
And that could create shockwaves, blast waves
或是宇宙射线爆发
Or bursts of cosmic rays
结局非常险恶
Which would have nasty consequences.
两系合并后
After the merger
我们太阳系的命运飘忽不定
The fate of our solar system is uncertain
当银河系和仙女系各自的超大质量黑洞
As the supermassive black holes of Andromeda and the Milky Way
在新形成的混乱星系里相互竞争
Vie for power in the newly jumbled galaxy.
星系合并时会形成一个新的星系
When they merge, they're gonna form a new galaxy
这两个超大质量黑洞
And these two supermassive black holes
也会逐渐盘旋着驻入新的星系中央
Will gradually spiral into the middle of the new galaxy.
一对黑洞的状态只保持很短一段时间
They will be a binary black hole for a short time.
这些黑洞开始吞食气体
And these black holes will start to swallow gas
冲撞搅起太空物质
As the collision stirs things up
太空气体夹着物质卷入黑洞
Gas will fall into those black holes.
物质被激发
They're gonna turn on.
开始迸发辐射线
They're gonna start emitting radiation.
烟尘潜在地为星系中央的黑洞
But the potential for fireworks, possibly for fueling the black holes
补充了能量
At the centers of the galaxies
物质像那样被卷入进去是可能的
Matter falling into them, possibilities like that do exist
观看这一过程唯一安全的地方
And then the only safe place to watch the process
就是其中一个"潮汐尾翼"
Would be on one of those tidal tails
安度并逃离冲撞
Riding out and escaping the collision.
一些科学家认为
Some scientists think that
仙女系的超大质量黑洞更大
Andromeda's larger supermassive black hole
将最终吞噬掉银河系的超大质量黑洞
Will eventually consume the Milky Way's.
两个黑洞先是盘旋在中央
The two black holes will spiral in the center
形成一对黑洞
And become a binary black hole
然后互相吞并
And ultimately, will merge with one another
形成一个更大的超大质量黑洞
To become yet an even bigger supermassive black hole.
所以 一个小星系撞击一个大星系
So, a small galaxy colliding with a large galaxy
小星系可能被大星系控制
Is likely to be dominated by the larger galaxy.
最终 小星系中的大量物质
It'll essentially have most of its material
被大星系吸收 附属在大星系之内
Absorbed by that galaxy and becomes subsumed into it.
科学家们认为星系吞并
Scientists believe galaxy mergers
是宇宙中的一种生命方式
Are a way of life in the Universe.
包括银河在内的现代星系
Modern galaxies, including the Milky Way
都是依靠吞并小星系来实现变大的
Have grown larger by cannibalizing smaller galaxies.
我们看见的每个星系
Every galaxy that we see
都可能是经历过多次星系撞击
Has probably been through many collisions.
银河系中央行星凸集
The Milky Way has a central bulge of stars,
这可能就是先前撞击后的遗迹
Which are, probably, the relic of a previous collision.
很多科学家一致认为
Most scientists agree that
银河系与仙女系间这场预期的大冲撞
the much anticipated merger between the Milky Way and Andromeda
至少在30亿年内不会发生
Won't happen for at least three billion years.
但太空中的近距摩擦危险会增多
But there may be more immediate dangers in space.
数百万光年远的宇宙近邻
In cosmic neighborhoods, millions of light-years away
存在极度活跃的星系
There are hyperactive galaxies
已成为对我们巨大的威胁
That have become the big bullies on the block.
在某些星系的中心住着宇宙怪兽
At the heart of some galaxies lives a cosmic monster.
它能把一个普通的星系转换成
It transforms a run-of-the-mill galaxy into
太空中最耀眼 最致命的星系
one of the brightest and deadliest in space.
"类星体"就是这种怪异的东西
Quasars are peculiar objects.
类星体由超大质量黑洞提供能量
Each powered by a supermassive black hole
黑洞会不停地吞食大量的物质
That continually swallows large amounts of matter
每年吞食10~20颗星体
10 to 20 stars every year.
类星体的核心处是个巨大的黑洞
At the core of these objects lives a very large black hole.
黑洞的任务就是
And the role of that black hole
产生大量的能量给类星体
Is to actually generate a huge amount of energy.
类星体拥有宇宙中最高效利用能量的机制
Quasars are the most energy-efficient mechanisms in the cosmos
它释放的能量比一百个普通星系还要多
They give off more power than a hundred normal galaxies.
比我们的太阳要亮十万亿倍
And they're 10 trillion times brighter than our Sun.
那么 类星体在宇宙中是怎么形成的呢？
So how are quasars created in the Universe?
上次的星系合并
There's a fairly good connection
和所谓的"类星体现象"之间
Between the last stages of a galactic merger
有着密切的联系
And the so-called "quasar phenomenon."
如果银河系与仙女系的真的发生的话
If that really happens in the case of the Milky Way and Andromeda
我们可能会产生
We could have
一个类星体活跃在合并星系的中心
For a period of some tens, even a hundred million years
持续几千万年甚至一亿年
A quasar active in the center of the merged galaxies.
类星体产出的能量约是
And a quasar puts out about a hundred times
一个普通星系的一百倍
As much energy as a typical galaxy.
如果我们被卷入一个
And if we were actually thrown into an orbit
带我们飞向星系中心的轨道
Which took us towards the center of the galaxy
我们就可能近距离接近类星体
We could get very close to that quasar
当然我们也会被烧焦
And really get scorched.
"类星体"这个词含义是"类似恒星的射电源"
The word "quasar" stands for "quasistellar radio source,"
意思是: 类似恒星的无线电波发射源
Which means star-like emitters of radio waves.
当类星体现象还是一个谜的时候
The word was coined
才创造了这个词
When the quasar phenomena was still a mystery.
现在我们知道它们一点也不像恒星
Now, we know they're not star-like at all.
除了放射无线电波和可见光
In addition to emitting radio waves and visible light
类星体还发出紫外线
Quasars also give off ultraviolet rays
红外线 X射线 伽马射线
Infrared waves, x-rays, and gamma rays
如果某物或某人靠得太近 将造成致命伤害
All deadlylf, something or someone gets too close.
类星体是一个很远的超大质量黑洞
A quasar is a supermassive black hole at large distance
但很活跃充满能量散发光芒
but it's is active, it's powerful, it's emitting light
我们可以在很多波带上发现它
And we can observe it in many wave bands.
类星体第一次被发现是在1960年代
Quasars were first discovered in the 1960s
但随着射电成像望远镜的技术日趋成熟
But as radio telescope imaging got better
天文学家发现有的类星体
Astronomers discovered that some of those quasars
也有强大的喷射光束
Also have powerful jets beaming out of them.
这种类星体叫做"耀类星体"
These particular quasars are called "blazars"
也许是宇宙中最激烈的现象
Probably some of the most violent phenomena in the Universe.
耀类星体跟类星体一样 靠黑洞提供能源
Blazars are powered by black holes just like quasars.
只是能量的分配有所不同 耀类星体的所有能量
But they're somewhat different in that all their energy
是集中到一起
Is being focused
或是大部分能量集中在
Or a large amount of their energy is being focused into
喷射光束上
jets which are streaming out.
耀类星体的高能等离子体喷柱
A blazar's aggressive plasma jets produce
产生的无线电波辐射
radiation in the form of radio waves
射频频谱从低一直高到
All the way through the spectrum
高能的伽马射线
Up to high-energy gamma rays.
天体物理学家格林·派勒
Astrophysicist Glenn Piner
曾调查过这些外来星系
Had been investigating the physical conditions
中心的实际情况
At the centers of these exotic galaxies.
我们可以用这口喷泉来比拟耀类星体
We can use this fountain to visualize the geometry of a blazar.
如果把喷泉的圆底座
If that circular base of the fountain
比作类星体圆盘
Represents the accretion disc
那么喷上来的水柱
Then the jet of water that's coming up
就代表来自类星体的等离子体喷柱
Represents the jet of plasma coming out from the blazar.
如果地球沿着喷水方向移动
And if the earth is sitting up in the direction that water is going
那么我们可以把它看成一个耀类星体
Then we would see this object as a blazar.
对天文学家来说 它看起来就像看一个火光四射的长管
For an astronomer, it's like looking down a fire hose.
看见它就会灼伤你的眼睛
It really gets you in the eye to see this bright
所以名叫"耀类星体"
Blazing thing that we call a "blazar."
耀类星体喷射移动得异常快
These blazar jets move exceptionally fast.
曾发现最快的能达到光速的99.9%
The fastest observed move at 99.9 percent the speed of light.
如果你拿着一个小东西
If you were to take a small object
像这个保龄球
Like this bowling ball
你想把它加速到
And you wanted to accelerate it
99.9%的光速
Up to 99.9 percent of the speed of light,
你将不得不把全地球产生的能量
You would have to give this bowling ball
全用在这个保龄球上
All the energy produced in the world
要保持一周才能达到99.9%的光速
For an entire week to accelerate it to that speed.
在这些耀类星体里
And in these blazars
我们不仅要把像保龄球样的小东西加速
We're accelerating not just small objects like bowling balls
而且还要将像木星之类大质量的或者比木星质量还大的
But large masses of the mass of the planet jupiter or larger
加速到那个速度
To those speeds
那这个高效的引擎需给它们施加
So they're being given incredible amounts of energy
偌大的能量
By this efficient engine.
耀类星体会对靠近它们喷射柱的物质
Blazars pose unimaginable consequences
造成难以想象的结果
To cosmic objects that get too close to its deadly jet.
如果有个行星靠得比较近
If there was a planet relatively close
离实际喷射柱几光年远
A few light-years from the actual jet
耀类星体对这个行星的辐射
The radiation on that planet
可能是附近恒星对它辐射的百万倍
Could be millions of times what it gets from the star.
它将长期曝露于高辐射环境下
It would be continually exposed to high levels of radiation.
所以我认为
So I don't think
想在行星上寻找生命
We wanna look for life on a planet
就不应在环绕耀类星体喷柱运行的行星上找
That would be orbiting a star, that's in a blazar jet.
科学家们把全球的射电望远镜连在一起
Scientists link radio telescopes all over the world
以达到放大耀类星体喷柱的效果
To achieve the magnification needed to zoom in on a blazar jet.
给你打个这种放大的类比
So to give you an analogy for what kind of magnification
这种放大效果可以在洛杉矶阅读
That would be magnification sufficient to read a newspaper
在纽约某人手中拿着的报纸
That someone was holding in New York from Los Angeles.
我们希望尽可能的观测到星系中央黑洞
We'd love to look as close to the central black hole as possible
那样我们才能得知它们是怎么
So we could actually figure out how nature
加速喷柱的
Is accelerating these jets
怎么使它们达到高速的
And getting them up to such high speeds.
我们也想知道
And we'd also like to know
那些喷柱实际是由什么构成的
What it is actually that the jets are made of
因为那种构成成分证明是某种
Because it turns out that's something
目前未知的东西
That's currently not known.
有待去发掘耀类星体
Until more is known about blazars
天文学家会在邻近地区关注它们
Astronomers will keep a neighborhood watch for them
关注我们未知宇宙中的
As well as all the other dangerous places
所有其它那些危险的地方
In our uncontrollable Universe.
可以肯定的是
Definitely
宇宙中的爆发事件从来没停过
There are violent events going on in the Universe
释放的能量大到超出我们的想象
Much, much more energy than we can even imagine on Earth.
比太阳亮万亿倍的光芒突然闪现
There are trillions of suns shining all at once.
那些就是我们谈论着的能量
Those are the kinds of energies that we're talking about.
但只要我们远离那些危险的地方
But in that case the fact that we are far away from them
就能安稳生存
Helps the survival of our species.
如果我们真的要遨游太空
If we're actually travelling through space
那么肯定的
Then, definitely
就要时刻注意这些危险
We will have to be worrying about these events.
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing